A Finding Aid to the Elizabeth McCausland Papers, 1838-1995, bulk 1920-1960, in the Archives of American Art AAA.mccaeliz
Archives of American Art
- Alfred H. Maurer, bulk 1948-1950; 1851-1951; Series 4; 3.7 Linear feet Boxes 6-9
  - Photographs Used for Dating Works, [1948-1949] (Box 9, Folder 25)
  - Plan for Maurer Exhibition, 1948 (Box 9, Folder 26-29)
  - Research (Box 9)
    - Period of 1933-1936, [1948-1949] (Box 9, Folder 30)
    - Period of 1937-1947, [1948-1949] (Box 9, Folder 31-32)
  - Research Material, Memorabilia, [1948-1949] (Box 9, Folder 33)
  - Research Material, Paintings, 1948-1949 (Box 9, Folder 34)
  - Research Material, Paintings (Box 9)
    - Executed 1905-1925, 1908, 1948-1949 (Box 9, Folder 35-36)
    - Executed 1925-1928, 1948-1949 (Box 9, Folder 37-38)
    - Executed 1928-1932, 1948-1949 (Box 9, Folder 39-40)
  - Research Material, Portraits, [1948-1949] (Box 9, Folder 41)
  - Research Notes, 1948 (Box 9, Folder 42-43)
  - Research Notes (Box 9)
    - Period of 1832-1900, 1851, 1933-1934, 1948-1949 (Box 9, Folder 44-45)
    - Period of 1901-1907, 1948-1949 (Box 9, Folder 46-47)
    - Period of 1908-1923, 1908-1909, 1948-1949 (Box 9, Folder 48-49)
    - Period of 1924-1930, 1924-1930, 1948-1949 (Box 9, Folder 50-51)
    - Period of 1931, 1931, 1948-1949 (Box 9, Folder 52)
    - Period of 1932, 1932, 1948-1949 (Box 9, Folder 53)
  - Research Notes, Maurer Correspondence (Box 9)
    - Period of 1899 and 1908-1923, 1899, 1908-1910, 1948-1949 (Box 9, Folder 54)
    - Period of 1924-1930, 1948-1949 (Box 9, Folder 55)
    - Period of 1931-1932, 1948-1949 (Box 9, Folder 56)
  - Reviews of Exhibition and Book, 1949, 1951 (Box 9, Folder 57)
  - System of Dating Works, 1949 (Box 9, Folder 58)
- American Processional, 1949-1951; Series 5; 1.8 Linear feet Boxes 10-11
  This series consists of files relating to McCausland's work as a research consultant on the exhibition, "American Processional, 1492-1900" at the Corcoran Gallery of Art, Washington, D.C., July 8-December 17, 1950, and as editor of the accompanying book. The exhibit was described as "a large exhibition of American life and history in pictures" and was planned in cooperation with the National Capital Sesquicentennial Commission "to commemorate the establishment of the permanent seat of the Federal Government in Washington in 1850." The book included two hundred illustrations of work from the exhibition with text comprised of "quotations from contemporaries of the events shown" and writing by McCausland. (These descriptions are drawn from a letter from McCausland to Norman Corwin dated June 20, 1950.)
  Files include research notes organized according to time period of the work of art, manuscripts and proofs of the book, catalog material, notes on sources and permissions, correspondence, and other research and publicity material.
  A large amount of correspondence relating to the American Processional can also be found in the General Correspondence series. A watercolor by Frank Buffmire documenting McCausland's contributions to the American Processional in a humorous fashion can be found amongst art work.
  Files are arranged in alphabetical order.
  This series is scanned in its entirety, except for galley and page proofs of the book.
  - American Processional (Box 10)
    - Alternate Cover, [1950] (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Editor's Copy, 1950 (Box 10, Folder 2-11)
    - End of the Book, 1950 (Box 10, Folder 12-14)
    - Galley Proofs, 1950 (Box 10, Folder 15-20)
    - Page Proofs, 1950 (Box 10, Folder 21)
    - Photograph Lists, 1950 (Box 10, Folder 22)
  - Bibliography, [1950] (Box 10, Folder 23)
  - Catalog, 1950 (Box 10, Folder 24)
  - Catalog, Chronology, 1949-1950 (Box 10, Folder 25)
  - Catalog Titles, 1950 (Box 10, Folder 26)
  - Correspondence, 1950 (Box 10, Folder 27-29)
  - [Correspondence], 1950 (Box 10, Folder 30)
  - Correspondence and Miscellaneous, 1950 (Box 10, Folder 31)
  - Folk Songs, [1950] (Box 10, Folder 32)
  - Installation, 1950 (Box 10, Folder 33)
  - [Lacunae and Sources and Permissions], [1950] (Box 10, Folder 34)
  - Laurel Printing Company, 1950 (Box 10, Folder 35-38)
  - Laurel Printing Company, Proofs, 1950 (Box 10, Folder 39-46)
  - Memos, 1950 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 1950 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - National Capital Sesquicentennial Commission, 1950-1951 (Box 11, Folder 3-4)
  - National Capital Sesquicentennial Commission, Catalog, 1949-1950 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Notebook, [1950] (Box 11, Folder 6-7)
  - Notes, 1949-1950 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Notes (Box 11)
    - Period of 1492-1643, [1950] (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - Period of 1645-1736, [1950] (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - Period of 1737-1774, [1950] (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - Period of 1775-1776, [1950] (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - Period of 1777-1799, [1950] (Box 11, Folder 13)
    - Period of 1825-1860, [1950] (Box 11, Folder 14)
    - Period of 1860-Summer 1863, [1950] (Box 11, Folder 15)
    - Period of Fall 1863-1865, [1950] (Box 11, Folder 16)
    - Period of 1866-1900, [1950] (Box 11, Folder 17)
    - Emblems and Insignias, [1950] (Box 11, Folder 18)
    - Miscellaneous, [1950] (Box 11, Folder 19)
  - Printer, 1950 (Box 11, Folder 20)
  - Publicity for Opening, 1950 (Box 11, Folder 21)
  - Research, 1950 (Box 11, Folder 22-24)
  - Review, [1950] (Box 11, Folder 25)
  - Slogans, [1950] (Box 11, Folder 26)
  - Sources and Permission, [1950] (Box 11, Folder 27)
  - Sources and Permissions - Period of 1861-1900, [1950] (Box 11, Folder 28)
  - Wall Labels, 1950 (Box 11, Folder 29-30)
- Marsden Hartley, bulk 1944-1964; 1900-1964; Series 6; 10 Linear feet Boxes 11-21, OV 37
  Series consists of extensive files relating to a major research project on the artist Marsden Hartley begun by the American Art Research Council around 1944 and turned over to McCausland by Hudson Walker in the early 1950s. The project involved a planned critical biography, envisaged as a companion volume to McCausland's biography of Maurer, and a projected catalogue raisonne of Hartley's paintings, neither of which was ever completed. Related projects included an introductory monograph on Hartley written by McCausland, focusing on the Hudson D. Walker collection of more than 150 Hartleys on long-term loan to the University of Minnesota, which was published in 1952; and a traveling exibition, organized by the Stedelijk Museum Amsterdam and American Federation of Arts, which took place from 1960 to 1962 and for which McCausland did the catalog.
  Some material may have been created and collected by the American Art Research Council, particularly portions of the catalogue raisonne files and other research files. McCausland seems to have incorporated this material into her own files and/or used and reorganized it as necessary in conjunction with creating and collecting material in her own files.
  The series is arranged as 6 subseries:
  6.1: Critical Biography Files, 1911-1964, bulk 1953-1964
  6.2: Catalogue Raisonne Files, circa 1946-1964
  6.3: Card Files, circa 1944-1964
  6.4: Correspondence and General Files, 1900-1964, bulk 1950-1964
  6.5: Other Research Files, 1921-1962, bulk 1944-1962
  6.6: Interviews, 1959-1960
  6.7: Auction Catalogs, 1905-1963, bulk 1905-1929
  The bulk of this series has been scanned, including photographs of works of art, except when obviously duplicate. Many of the photographs of works of art in this series include annotations and research notes on the reverse or relate so closely to the research notes that the decision was made to scan them. Identyfing the duplicate photographs was difficult, thus many have been scanned. The card files of McCausland's indexes have not been scanned, nor were auction catalogs. In many cases, only the covers and title pages of publications were scanned.
  - Critical Biography Files, bulk 1953-1964; 1911-1964; 6.1
    Subseries consists of files relating to McCausland's work researching and writing a planned critical biography of the artist Marsden Hartley. McCausland began work on the biography sometime after her monograph on Hartley was published in 1952. She worked on the Hartley biography for several years off and on up until her death in 1965, though it was never completed. Files are primarily comprised of notes on Hartley's life and work (organized according to time period), as well as some research material, including typescripts and some originals of Hartley's letters, exhibition catalogs and other printed material, and scattered papers belonging to Hudson Walker and relating to Hartley. Also found are an outline and a manuscript of Chapters 1-3 of the planned biography, and some notes and research material on exhibitions, memorabilia, and portaits.
    Most of the material is undated, yet it can be reasonably assumed that it was collected and created during the time period from 1953 to 1964, roughly when McCausland was working on the biography.
    Files are arranged in alphabetical order. Related material can be found in correspondence and general files and other research files within this series. This material was most likely originally kept in notebooks, but was removed from them at some previous point in time, perhaps during preliminary processing.
    This subseries has been scanned in its entirety.
    - Exhibitions, circa 1953-1964 (Box 11, Folder 31)
    - Manuscript, [circa 1953-1964] (Box 11, Folder 32-34)
    - Memorabilia, circa 1953-1964 (Box 11, Folder 35)
    - Notes (Box 11)
      - Period of 1877-1892, [circa 1953-1964] (Box 11, Folder 36-37)
      - Period of 1893-1908, [circa 1953-1964] (Box 11, Folder 38-41)
      - Period of 1908, [circa 1953-1964] (Box 12, Folder 1)
      - Period of 1909, [circa 1953-1964] (Box 12, Folder 2-4)
      - Period of 1910, [circa 1953-1964] (Box 12, Folder 5)
      - Period of 1911, [circa 1953-1964] (Box 12, Folder 6)
      - Period of 1912, [circa 1953-1964] (Box 12, Folder 7-10)
      - Period of 1913, [circa 1953-1964] (Box 12, Folder 11-12)
      - Period of 1914, [circa 1953-1964] (Box 12, Folder 13-14)
      - Period of 1915, [circa 1953-1964] (Box 12, Folder 15)
      - Period of 1916, [circa 1953-1964] (Box 12, Folder 16)
      - Period of 1917, [circa 1953-1964] (Box 12, Folder 17)
      - Period of 1918, [circa 1953-1964] (Box 12, Folder 18-20)
      - Period of 1919, [circa 1953-1964] (Box 12, Folder 21-22)
      - Period of 1920, [circa 1953-1964] (Box 12, Folder 23-24)
      - Period of 1921, [circa 1953-1964] (Box 12, Folder 25)
      - Period of 1922, [circa 1953-1964] (Box 12, Folder 26)
      - Period of 1923, [circa 1953-1964] (Box 12, Folder 27-28)
      - Period of 1924, [circa 1953-1964] (Box 12, Folder 29)
      - Period of 1925, [circa 1953-1964] (Box 12, Folder 30)
      - Period of 1926, [circa 1953-1964] (Box 12, Folder 31)
      - Period of 1927, [circa 1953-1964] (Box 12, Folder 32)
      - Period of 1928, [circa 1953-1964] (Box 12, Folder 33)
      - Period of 1929, [circa 1953-1964] (Box 12, Folder 34)
      - Period of 1930, [circa 1953-1964] (Box 12, Folder 35)
      - Period of 1931, [circa 1953-1964] (Box 12, Folder 36-38)
      - Period of 1932, [circa 1953-1964] (Box 12, Folder 39)
      - Period of 1933, [circa 1953-1964] (Box 12, Folder 40-42)
      - Period of 1934, [circa 1953-1964] (Box 12, Folder 43)
      - Period of 1935, [circa 1953-1964] (Box 12, Folder 44)
      - Period of 1936, [circa 1953-1964] (Box 13, Folder 1-2)
      - Period of 1937, [circa 1953-1964] (Box 13, Folder 3-4)
      - Period of 1938, [circa 1953-1964] (Box 13, Folder 5)
      - Period of 1939-1940, [circa 1953-1964] (Box 13, Folder 6-7)
      - Period of 1940, 1940, [circa 1953-1964] (Box 13, Folder 8)
      - Period of 1941, 1941, [circa 1953-1964] (Box 13, Folder 9)
      - Period of 1942, 1942, [circa 1953-1964] (Box 13, Folder 10)
      - Period of 1943-1946, [circa 1953-1964] (Box 13, Folder 11-13)
    - Outline, [circa 1953-1964] (Box 13, Folder 14)
    - Portraits, 1927, 1944-1959 (Box 13, Folder 15-18)
      Oversized item in OV 37
    - Oversize, Portrait, 1927 (Box OV 37)
      Scanned with Box 13, Folder 16
  - Catalogue Raisonne Files, circa 1944-1964; 6.2
    Subseries consists of extensive files relating to the planned published catalogue raisonne of Hartley paintings. Files were probably started circa 1944 by the American Art Research Council and were eventually taken over, used, and added to by McCausland up until the time before her death. Files consist of photographs of and research forms for individual Hartley paintings, as well as some scattered notes and printed material.
    Files are arranged chronologically according to the year of execution of the artwork, and then according to subject type and/or technique of painting. The dates specified in the brackets represent the probable creation or collation date of the file.
    Almost all of the photographs of works of art have been scanned in this subseries due to the many annotations and similar versions of paintings. It is impossible to determine with certainty which photographs may be duplicates, so all were scanned.
    - Research Files, 1900 (Box 13)
      - Nudes and Figures, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 13, Folder 19)
    - Research Files, before 1908 (Box 13)
      - Landscapes, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 13, Folder 20)
      - "Walt Whitman's House,", [circa 1944-1964] (Box 13, Folder 21)
    - Research Files, 1908 (Box 13)
      - Drawings, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 13, Folder 22)
      - Landscapes (Box 13)
        - Drawings, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 13, Folder 23)
        - Oils, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 13, Folder 24-27)
        - Watercolors, Pastels, Prints, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 13, Folder 28)
      - Nudes and Figures - Drawings, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 13, Folder 29-31)
      - Watercolors, Pastels, and Prints, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 13, Folder 32)
    - Research Files, 1909 (Box 13)
      - Drawings, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 13, Folder 33)
      - Landscapes (Box 13)
        - Drawings, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 13, Folder 34)
        - Oils, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 13, Folder 35-37)
    - Research Files, 1910 (Box 13)
      - Still Life (Box 13)
        - Oils, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 13, Folder 38)
        - Watercolors, Pastels, Prints, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 13, Folder 39)
    - Research Files, 1911 (Box 13)
      - Still Life (Box 13)
        - Oils, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 13, Folder 40-41)
        - Watercolors, Pastels, Prints, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 13, Folder 42)
      - Watercolors, Pastels, Prints, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 13, Folder 43)
    - Research Files, 1912 (Box 13)
      - Still Life (Box 13)
        - Drawings, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 13, Folder 44)
        - Oils, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 13, Folder 45-46)
      - Watercolors, Pastels, Prints, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 13, Folder 47)
    - Research Files, 1912/1913 (Box 13)
      - Still Life - Oils, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 13, Folder 48-49)
    - Research Files, 1913 (Box 14)
      - Still Life - Oils, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 14, Folder 1-2)
    - Research Files, 1914 (Box 14)
      - Still Life - Oils, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Research Files, 1914-1915 (Box 14)
      - Still Life - Oils, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 14, Folder 4)
      - "Indian Fantasy,", 1960 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Research Files, 1915 (Box 14)
      - Still Life - Oils, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - Research Files, 1916 (Box 14)
      - Still Life - Oils, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 14, Folder 7-9)
    - Research Files, 1917 (Box 14)
      - Still Life - Oils, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 14, Folder 10-11)
    - Research Files, 1918 (Box 14)
      - Landscapes - Watercolors, Pastels, Prints, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 14, Folder 12-13)
      - Still Life (Box 14)
        - Oils, 1960 (Box 14, Folder 14)
        - Watercolors, Pastels, Prints, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 14, Folder 15)
    - Research Files, 1919 (Box 14)
      - Landscapes - Watercolors, Pastels, Prints, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 14, Folder 16)
      - Still Life (Box 14)
        - Oils, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 14, Folder 17)
        - Watercolors, Pastels, Prints, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 14, Folder 18)
    - Research Files, 1920 (Box 14)
      - Landscapes - Oils, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 14, Folder 19-20)
      - Still Life, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 14, Folder 21-23)
    - Research Files, 1922 (Box 14)
      - Nudes and Figures (Box 14)
        - Drawings, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 14, Folder 24)
        - Oils, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 14, Folder 25)
        - Watercolors, Pastels, Prints, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 14, Folder 26)
      - Still Life - Drawings, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 14, Folder 27)
    - Research Files, 1922-1923 (Box 14)
      - Landscapes - Oils, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 14, Folder 28-30)
      - Still Life (Box 14)
        - Oils, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 14, Folder 31)
        - Watercolors, Pastels, Prints, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 14, Folder 32)
    - Research Files, 1923 (Box 14)
      - Still Life (Box 14)
        - Drawings, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 14, Folder 33)
        - Oils, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 14, Folder 34)
        - Watercolors, Pastels, Prints, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 14, Folder 35-36)
    - Research Files, 1924 (Box 14)
      - Still Life - Oils, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 14, Folder 37)
    - Research Files, 1924-1925 (Box 14)
      - Still Life - Oils, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 14, Folder 38)
    - Research Files, 1925 (Box 14)
      - Landscape - Oils, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 14, Folder 39)
      - Still Life - Oils, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 14, Folder 40)
    - Research Files, 1925-1926 (Box 14)
      - Landscapes - Oils, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 14, Folder 41)
    - Research Files, 1926 (Box 14)
      - Landscape - Drawings, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 14, Folder 42)
      - Still Life (Box 14)
        - Drawings, 1953 (Box 14, Folder 43)
        - Oils, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 14, Folder 44)
    - Research Files, 1927 (Box 14)
      - Landscapes (Box 14)
        - Drawings, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 14, Folder 45-46)
        - Oils, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 14, Folder 47)
      - Still Life (Box 14)
        - Drawings, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 14, Folder 48)
        - Watercolors, Pastels, Prints, [1944-1965] (Box 14, Folder 49)
    - Research Files, 1928 (Box 14)
      - Still Life - Oils, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 14, Folder 50)
    - Research Files, 1929 (Box 14)
      - Still Life (Box 14)
        - Drawings, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 14, Folder 51)
        - Oils, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 14, Folder 52-54)
    - Research Files, 1930 (Box 15)
      - Landscapes - Oils, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 15, Folder 1-2)
    - Research Files, 1931 (Box 15)
      - Landscapes (Box 15)
        - Drawings, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 15, Folder 3)
        - Oils, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 15, Folder 4)
        - Watercolors, Pastels, Prints, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 15, Folder 5)
      - Still Life - Oils, [1944-1965] (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - Research Files, 1932 (Box 15)
      - Landscapes - Oils, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 15, Folder 7)
        Partially scanned
      - Still Life - Oils, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 15, Folder 8)
    - Research Files, 1932/1933 (Box 15)
      - Landscapes - Oils, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 15, Folder 9)
      - Still Life - Oils, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 15, Folder 10)
    - Research Files, 1933 (Box 15)
      - Landscapes (Box 15)
        - Drawings, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 15, Folder 11)
        - Oils, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 15, Folder 12)
        - Watercolors, Pastels, Prints, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 15, Folder 13)
      - Still Life - Oils, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 15, Folder 14)
    - Research Files, 1933/1934 (Box 15)
      - Landscapes - Oils, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 15, Folder 15)
    - Research Files, 1934 (Box 15)
      - Landscapes (Box 15)
        - Drawings, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 15, Folder 16)
        - Oils, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 15, Folder 17-18)
        - Watercolors, Pastels, Prints, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 15, Folder 19)
      - Still Life - Oils, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 15, Folder 20)
    - Research Files, 1935 (Box 15)
      - Still Life - Watercolors, Pastels, Prints, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 15, Folder 21)
      - Landscapes - Drawings, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 15, Folder 22)
    - Research Files, 1935/1936 (Box 15)
      - Still Life - Oils, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 15, Folder 23)
    - Research Files, 1936 (Box 15)
      - Landscape (Box 15)
        - Drawings, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 15, Folder 24)
        - Oils, [1944-1965 (Box 15, Folder 25-26)
      - Nudes and Figures - Drawings, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 15, Folder 27)
      - Still Life (Box 15)
        - Drawings, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 15, Folder 28)
        - Oils, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 15, Folder 29-30)
        - Watercolors, Pastels, Prints, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 15, Folder 31)
    - Research Files, 1937 (Box 15)
      - Landscapes (Box 15)
        - Drawings, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 15, Folder 32)
        - Oils, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 15, Folder 33-35)
      - Still Life - Oils, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 15, Folder 36)
    - Research Files, 1938 (Box 15)
      - Landscapes (Box 15)
        - Drawings, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 15, Folder 37)
        - Oils, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 15, Folder 38-40)
      - Nudes and Figures (Box 15)
        - Drawings, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 15, Folder 41)
        - Oils, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 15, Folder 42-44)
      - Still Life - Oils, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 15, Folder 45)
    - Research Files, 1939 (Box 15)
      - Landscapes (Box 15)
        - Drawings, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 15, Folder 46-47)
        - Oils, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 15, Folder 48)
      - Nudes and Figures (Box 15)
        - Drawings, 1953 (Box 15, Folder 49)
        - Oils, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 15, Folder 50)
      - Still Life - Oils, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 15, Folder 51)
    - Research Files, 1939/1940 (Box 15)
      - Landscapes - Oils, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 15, Folder 52-53)
      - Nudes and Figures - Oils, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 15, Folder 54)
    - Research Files, 1940 (Box 15)
      - Landscapes (Box 15)
        - Drawings, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 15, Folder 55-56)
        - Oils, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 15, Folder 57)
      - Nudes and Figures (Box 15)
        - Drawings, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 15, Folder 58)
        - Oils, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 15, Folder 59)
        - Watercolors, Pastels, Prints, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 15, Folder 60)
      - Still Life (Box 15)
        - Drawings, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 15, Folder 61)
        - Oils, 1951 (Box 15, Folder 62)
        - Watercolors, Pastels, Prints, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 15, Folder 63)
    - Research Files, 1940/1941 (Box 16)
      - Landscapes - Oils, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 16, Folder 1)
      - Nudes and Figures - Oils, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 16, Folder 2)
      - Still Life - Oils, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - Research Files, 1941 (Box 16)
      - Landscapes - Oils, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 16, Folder 4)
      - Nudes and Figures - Oils, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 16, Folder 5)
      - Still Life - Oils, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 16, Folder 6-7)
    - Research Files, 1942 (Box 16)
      - Landscapes - Oils, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 16, Folder 8)
      - Nudes and Figures (Box 16)
        - Drawings, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 16, Folder 9)
        - Oils, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 16, Folder 10)
      - Still Life - Oils, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 16, Folder 11-12)
    - Research Files, 1943 (Box 16)
      - Nudes and Figures (Box 16)
        - Drawings, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 16, Folder 13)
        - Oils, 1951 (Box 16, Folder 14)
      - Still Life - Oils, [circa 1944-1964] (Box 16, Folder 15)
  - Card Files, circa 1944-1964; 6.3
    Subseries consists of McCausland's card files for her Hartley study. Card files include indexes to titles and owners of Hartley works, as well as to the artist's correspondence, exhibitions, and events in his life. The card files have not been scanned.
    This subseries has not been scanned.